<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A visitation sermon preached at the Lord Archbishops trienniall and ordinary visitation, in St. Margarets in Canterbury, vpon Aprill the fift, 1630. By Francis Rogers, Doctor in Diuinity, and minister of that parish.</title>
            <author>Rogers, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116094</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851311</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851311</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16582</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10906)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16582)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1332:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A visitation sermon preached at the Lord Archbishops trienniall and ordinary visitation, in St. Margarets in Canterbury, vpon Aprill the fift, 1630. By Francis Rogers, Doctor in Diuinity, and minister of that parish.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Norton, for William Adderton, and are to bee sold at his shop in Bethlem without Bishops-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visitation sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16582:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16582:1"/>
            <p>A VISITATION SERMON, Preached at the Lord Archbiſhops trienniall and ordinary Viſitation, In <hi>St. Margarets</hi> in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> vpon <hi>Aprill</hi> the fift, 1630.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis Rogers,</hi> Doctor in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity, and Miniſter of that Pariſh.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLESIASTES 12.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Preacher did ſeeke out pleaſant words.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Norton,</hi> for <hi>William Adderton,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Bethlem</hi> without <hi>Biſhopſ-gate.</hi> 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16582:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16582:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, <hi>George,</hi> Lord <hi>Arch-biſhop of Canterbury his</hi> Grace, Primate of all <hi>England,</hi> and Metropolitane.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon was lately preached at your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Viſitation; and now being willing to ſhew it ſelfe vnto others, aſwell as vnto thoſe that heard it, preſents it ſelfe with all humility to your gracious hands, deſiring to giue it your bleſſing, before it walke abroad, euen That with which <hi>Iacob</hi> ſent his ſonnes into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> that God would giue it mercy
<pb facs="tcp:16582:3"/>
in the ſight of the man; in the ſight of the Schiſmaticall man, to make him conformable; in the ſight of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable man, to keepe in ſtraight paths; in the ſight of the idle Shepherd, to ſtirre him vp to feede Gods Flocke; in the ſight of the paynefull Labourer, not to pull his hand from the plow, but to perſeuere in Gods harueſt: So God continue to direct your Grace in all weighty affaires, to Gods glory, and the good of his Church, and your owne ſoules comfort.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces moſt bounden,</hi> Francis Rogers.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16582:3"/>
            <head>A Viſitation Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, preached at the Lord <hi>Archbiſhops trienniall and ordinary Viſitation.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ECCLESIASTES 12.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Preacher did ſeeke out pleaſant words.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is much controuerſed betwixt vs and the Papiſts, whether <hi>Salomon</hi> were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. The reaſons on both ſides, made <hi>Petrus Tenerius,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> to cauſe his paynter, to picture in his Chappell, heauen and hell, and to place <hi>Salomon</hi> in the middeſt, one halfe in hell, the other halfe in heauen. For mine owne part, I had rather beleeue <hi>Saul</hi> is ſaued then <hi>Salomon</hi> damned: the Canon of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will inſtruct mee for the one, and there is no Canon of certitude to warrant me for the other. But I meane
<pb facs="tcp:16582:4"/>
to omit this, and all other things touching this Booke: and at this time onely to accommodate my ſelfe to this preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>In theſe words therefore I note three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, who this Preacher was, cap. 1.12. <hi>I the Preacher was King ouer Iſrael:</hi> and hence I note the dignity and honour of the Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I note the labour and trauell appertaining to this calling in, <hi>did ſeeke out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, I note the wiſedome and diſcretion ſhould be in this calling, <hi>non magno conatu nugas peragere,</hi> like <hi>Mirmerides</hi> and <hi>Mileſius</hi> in <hi>Aeliau,</hi> who made wagons for a Fly to draw: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe things are nothing but loſſe of time. But my <hi>Preacher ſought out pleaſant words,</hi> that is, in the end of this verſe, <hi>words of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So theſe three things I purpoſe by Gods grace and your patience, to treate of at this time, namely, the <list>
                  <item>Dignity</item>
                  <item>Labour</item>
                  <item>Wiſedome</item>
               </list>
of the Prieſt, and Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>For the dignity: <hi>I the Preacher was King ouer Iſrael;</hi> and he calleth himſelfe in this booke, ſeuen times by the name of <hi>Preacher.</hi> Wee are called in the Bible, <hi>Gods Ambaſſadours, ſhining starres, Reuel.</hi> 2.3. wee are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Angels,</hi> becauſe as Gods Angels were wont to bring Gods meſſages to man: ſo the Miniſters doe preach glad tydings of ſaluation in Chriſt. Hence the godly did alwaies giue all honourable titles to Gods Prieſts. <hi>Sara</hi> called <hi>Abraham</hi> Lord. <hi>Hannah</hi> call'd <hi>Ely</hi> Lord. The wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow called <hi>Elias</hi> Lord. The Iewes neuer almoſt ſpake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Sauiour, but they cald him Lord, Maſter, or <hi>Rabbi.</hi> The coſtly garment appoynted by God himſelfe, for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aron</hi> to weare, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. ſheweth in what high eſteeme the
<pb facs="tcp:16582:4"/>
Prieſt ſhould bee. Come we to the heathen men. The <hi>Phaenices</hi> allowed their Prieſt onely to weare Gold, and Purple robes, downe to the feete: and in token of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of greater honour, hee wore a Crowne of Gold and precious Stones. The Prieſt of <hi>Hercules</hi> was cloathed in Purple, wearing a Miter, and he was next in honour vnto the King. Among the <hi>Romanes,</hi> Kings were wont to vndergoe the Office of Prieſts: and when the Kings ceaſed, it was vnlawfull to create Prieſts of any which were not of the Senate Houſe. <hi>Flamen Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> which was <hi>Iupiters</hi> High Prieſt, was arrayed with a coſtly garment, hee was to ride in his Chariot: if any had beene brought bound in his houſe, hee was to bee looſed, in honour of the Prieſt: if any had beene carried to puniſhment, and had fallen downe humbly at his feete, it had beene great ſinne that day to ſtrike him. The Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> was the Kingly Tribe, and none might marry into that Tribe but <hi>Leui.</hi> Hence came <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the High Prieſt to be of the Blood-royall, and Vncle to King <hi>Ioaſh.</hi> But the Prieſts greateſt honour is in <hi>Iob</hi> 33. verſe 23, 24. <hi>If there be with him a Meſſenger an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter, one of a thouſand to declare vnto men his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Then will he haue mercy on him: and will ſay, Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him, that he goe not downe into the pit, for I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a reconciliation.</hi> In which words we ſee, that authority is giuen to the Miniſter, to redeeme a penitent ſoule from hell and damnation: and this is the greateſt honour that euer was giuen to any creature.</p>
            <p>Angels gaue the Law at Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> Angels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed the birth of Chriſt. Angels haue often brought glad meſſages from God to man. But it was neuer ſayd to Angell, Deliuer that man, that he goe not downe into the pit. To ſome callings God ſayth, Worke thou for man, Build him houſes, Prouide him ſuſtenance. To the Phyſician, Heale the man. To the Lawyer, Pleade for the man. To the Souldier, Fight for the man. To the
<pb facs="tcp:16582:5"/>
Magiſtrate, Defend him. To the King, Gouerne him. To none but to the Miniſter, Deliuer him, that he goe no downe into the pit. But, though this function bee ſo excellent, yet wee may not ſay, as it is in the Popes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees: As the Sunne in glory exceedeth the Moone, ſo doth the Pope excell the Emperour. Nor as <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that Kings are not onely ſubiect to Popes, to Biſhops, to Prieſts, but euen to Deacons: that an Emperour muſt content himſelfe not onely to drinke after a Biſhop, but after a Biſhops Chaplaine: if they are as they haue beene called diſeaſed Prieſts, this were a ſlouenly and a hard penance for a King to performe. And againe, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that are but Popes Vaſſals, may depoſe Kings, and abrogate their Lawes. Theſe things proceede out of the mouth that ſpeaketh blaſphemy, and they ſauour one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of that man of ſinne, which doth ſit in the Church of God, and exalt himſelfe aboue God, and aboue all that is called Gods.</p>
            <p>But we hold it for a truth vndeniable, that Kings may, as did <hi>Salomon,</hi> depoſe <hi>Abiathar</hi> the High Prieſt, and place <hi>Zadok</hi> in his roome. And therefore though the Prieſt bee ſo excellent, yet let euery ſoule bee ſubiect to the higher powers, and that for conſcience ſake: and if euery ſoule, then your ſoule. So ſayth <hi>Bernard</hi> to Pope <hi>Eugenius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This our calling ſo honorable, ſerueth, Firſt, to inſtruct our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Secondly, others.</p>
            <p>For our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Is this our calling ſo excellent? Then know, <hi>Generatio optima, corruptio peſſima,</hi> The beſt things corrupted, proue the worſt: for <hi>Omnis corruptio eſt in contrarium,</hi> all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption is into the contrary: See by the Angels, moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in their creation, moſt loathſome in their degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. As I hold none more to bee reuerenced, then a good Miniſter: ſo, none more baſe, then one deboſhed
<pb facs="tcp:16582:5"/>
in his life. Thus our Sauiour, <hi>Yee are the Salt of the earth, but if the Salt be vnſauoury, it is fit for nothing, but to be caſt on the dunghill, and trod vnder foote.</hi> Then, as we are the light of the world: So, <hi>Our light muſt ſhine before others, that they ſeeing our good workes, may learne to glorifie our Father which is in Heauen. Ille granditer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, qui non contemptibiliter viuit,</hi> He preacheth well, that doth not liue contemptibly, ſayth <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Among <hi>Grammarians,</hi> he is excellent that can ſpeak well: for Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar is an art of ſpeaking. But among Deuines, not onely words, but workes are required. <hi>Turpe eſt doctori, cum culpa redarguit ipſum:</hi> Men (ſayth <hi>Lactantius</hi>) had rather haue good examples then good words, for it is eaſie to ſpeake well, but hard to doe well. Prieſts muſt be <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barij, et operarij:</hi> preaching in doctrine and in life: for <hi>Ille ſolom praedicat viua voce, qui praedicat vita et voce:</hi> He only preacheth with a liuely voyce, which preacheth with his life and voyce. <hi>Omnia in ſacerdote debent eſſe vocalia,</hi> ſayth Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> All things in a Diuine muſt preach, his apparrell muſt preach, his Diet muſt preach, his pleaſures muſt preach, all his life muſt preach, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Hee muſt bee an enſample in word, in conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in ſpirit, in fayth, in pureneſſe. Quid Antiſtes ad dominum, niſi pro delictis populi Interceſſor eligitur,</hi> ſayth <hi>Gregory?</hi> Why is the Miniſter choſen, but to intercede for the people, and to reconcile the people to God? And with what confidence dare hee preſume to reconcile others to God, when himſelfe is vnreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by his wickedneſſe? Will one enemy reconcile a third perſon to his vtter enemy? <hi>Sacerdotis Chriſtios, mens, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſque concordent:</hi> The hands, the mouth, and the minde of the Miniſter of Chriſt muſt agree together, ſayth <hi>Ierome, Sic oculos, ſic ille manus, ſic ora fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A learned Fryer, at a Councell, complayning of the
<pb facs="tcp:16582:6"/>
abuſe of the Clergy, preaching before the Emperour, wiſhed him to begin reformation of the Clergy <hi>a minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> from the inferiour ſort of Clergy. The Emperour thanked him for his Sermon, and ſayd, He had rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>a maioribus,</hi> from the better ſort of Clergy. So, the more eminent a Clergy man, the more ſhining let him bee in vertuous liuing. Miniſters are like great ſtones in a building: if one ſtone in the ſide of this Church fall, there will follow a Cart-load of rubbiſh after. So, one bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a Miniſter, eſpecially of a great one, will cauſe thouſands of poore ſheepe to fall into the ditch: and we muſt redreſſe the ſmalleſt faults.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarke</hi> reporteth, <hi>Cymon</hi> a iuſt man was blemiſhed, becauſe he dranke wine. <hi>Pompey</hi> the great was eſteemed effeminate, becauſe he ſcratched his head with one finger. Worthy <hi>Scipio</hi> was checked, becauſe hee was giuen to ſleepe much. And ſo moates in Preachers will be iudged beames: For as <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Dead Flies</hi> (and a Fly is but a ſmall creature) <hi>cauſe to ſtinke, and putrifie the Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Apothecary.</hi> So, <hi>a little folly, him that is in eſtimation for wiſedome and glory.</hi> So, wee eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of all men, ſhould make vſe of the Italian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, <hi>The want of a nayle, is the loſſe of a ſhoo: the loſſe of a ſhoo, the hurt of an horſe: the hurt of an horſe, the death of a Captaine: the death of a Captaine, the ouerthrow of an Army: the ouerthrow of an Army, the vtter ruine and deſolation of a whole Kingdome.</hi> There is a Fable, <hi>That the Axe wanted an helue, and comming to a great Wood, begged onely ſo much wood as to make the helue: alledging that it would be no hurt to the Wood which was ſo great, and that parcell of wood ſo ſmall: this being granted, no ſoone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was the helue fitted to the Axe, but preſently the Axe did cut downe the whole Wood.</hi> And ſo take we heede, how wee harbour the ſmalleſt faults, and giue ſcandall in the leaſt things: for time may come, that theſe in the end may
<pb facs="tcp:16582:6"/>
grow ſo big, as That euill doome may befall the Church, which did in <hi>Henry</hi> the eyghth his time: which God in his mercy preuent. Nay, to auoyd from ſcandall, wee ought to abſtaine euen <hi>a licitis,</hi> from things lawfull. For as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> obſerueth, That which is a vertue in God, is oftentimes a ſinne in man. For example, it was infinite mercy in God, to forgiue <hi>Dauids</hi> murder and adultery: but it would be a blot in iuſtice, to a King to pardon ſuch a double offence in any ſubiect. So, what is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in others, will be vicious in vs. Therefore Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> rule is true, <hi>Though all things are lawfull, yet all things are not expedient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a foule ſinne in <hi>Balaam,</hi> to bee both ambitious and auaricious: but it was more foule in him, ſo to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere that his Aſſe ſhould bee wiſer then himſelfe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to proue him. So, it is euill in the Clergy to bee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their conuerſation: but it is too bad, when they grow to ſuch an height, as that the aſſes of this age, the ſimple Artificer, and plaine Countreyman ſhall be able to diſcerne and condemne him, and poynt with the finger, ſaying, <hi>Ditior hic eſt,</hi> there is one which is a lewd Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, one which is ſcandalous in his conuerſation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the people.</p>
            <p>Is our calling ſo honourable, as to be Gods Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours? Then ought yee to reuerence our perſons, and honour our function: <hi>He which deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me: but he which receiueth a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, ſhall haue a Prophets reward.</hi> But alaſſe, our Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are like the <hi>Romanes</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>de ciu. Dei, cap. vlt.</hi> They could allow of Playes to be act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in honour of their gods, but they eſteemed thoſe which acted them, to bee moſt baſe. So, wee allow of Prayers, preaching, &amp;c. but theſe which are ſet apart for ſuch dueties, are eſteemed men of the meaneſt ranke and condition. Vnder the Law, the Kings would be Prophets, and ſonnes of Kings would ſerue at the Altar: Nay,
<pb facs="tcp:16582:7"/>
Chriſt the Sonne of God tooke vpon him the Office of a Prieſt in the Church of Rome. Dukes, Earles, and Nobles deſire admittance into holy orders. But among vs a Gentleman, an elder brother a Prieſt, were <hi>Rara auis in terris, nigro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſimillima Cygno:</hi> you may as ſoone ſee a blacke Swan ſwim downe the riuer, nay but for neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, none of a Gentle family: and yet were it not for the Prieſthood, there would be many a hundred poore beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly Gentlemen which now liue in good repute, and vphold the honour of the family with the Elder brother: and thus it commeth to paſſe oftentimes, that when lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and honeſty abound, the Miniſter is contemned by reaſon of his birth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herodotus</hi> reporteth, that in the temple of <hi>Apollo</hi> were veſſels of gold and ſiluer, wherein they ſacrificed to their gods: and other veſſels of pewter and tinne, which ſerued for other vſes: in proceſſe of time, the temple being robbed of the richer veſſels, they were conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to vſe the meaner, which though in themſelues but meane, yet they were eſteemed of highly, becauſe they were ordayned for holy vſes. So, admit the birth of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be meane and obſcure, yet if they bee ſet apart to preach the Goſpell, eſteeme them not as they are in birth, ſonnes of obſcure parents: but as they are in Office, Prieſts of the moſt high God: Knowing, that none dare to reſiſt a poore Bozholder, the meaneſt officer, but his contempt is to the King himſelfe. And I could wiſh, that our contempt did not oftentimes ariſe from our owne Coate. Which of our great Prophets will make his ſonne a Prophet, and match into the houſes of other Prophets? Nay, as many Lay Gentlemen obſerue, They which ſhould vphold the honour of our Coate, bring the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne, in regard the Great perſonages in the Church, diſdayne to countenance the poore Clergy. We poore country Miniſters are the legges and feete, whereon the ſhoulders and armes of the great Churchmen ſtand. But
<pb facs="tcp:16582:7"/>
I wiſh theſe to remember, that if a man catch cold in the feete, it will quickly ſtrike vp into the head, and ſo, if contempt light on vs the Feete, it will ſoone poſſeſſe the Heads, and great Ones too: ſo here, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Let men ſo eſteeme of vs, as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of the ſecrets of God.</hi> For, art thou beholding to him, who when thou haſt loſt a Iewell of much valew, findeth it for thee? To a Lawyer, for pleading thy cauſe? To a Phyſician, for recouering thy health? Then much more eſteeme of him, who when thy ſoule is loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> doth redeeme it out of the pit, and hell of damnation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I obſerued in this text, is, The Preachers labour and trauaile, <hi>he did ſeeke out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was not my Preacher a King, and ſo, higher then a Pope? Had hee not learning and wiſedome in abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dant manner? He did ſwim in wealth: and then, what madneſſe was it in him to bee laborious and painefull? I, but my Preacher eſteemed no wiſedome, nor lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning comparable, to winne ſoules, and inſtruct Gods people. And therefore, verſe 9. <hi>The more wiſe the Preacher was, the more hee taught the people knowledge, and cauſed them to heare, and ſearched forth, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red many parables.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>If any deſire the Office of a Biſhop, he deſireth a worthy worke.</hi> The name Biſhop, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in minde of the great labour and trauell belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to that Function. <hi>Epiſcopus eſt ſpeculator, obſeruator, et cuſtos, et praefectus:</hi> A Biſhop is a Watchman, an Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer, a Superintendent: all which words import a labour and trauaile, pertayning to the Function. Thus <hi>Tully ad Atticum, Vult me Pompeius eſſe, quem tota haec Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, et maritima ora habeant, Epiſcopum ad quem delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus et negotij ſumma referatur. Pompey</hi> would haue mee him, whom this region and the Seacoaſts ſhould haue their Biſhop, to whom the choyce and chiefe buſineſſe ſhould be committed. Thus the <hi>Athenians</hi> called them
<pb facs="tcp:16582:8"/>
whom they ſent to view the diſorders of their Cities, Biſhops. Hence Saint <hi>Auguſtine lib. de ciuit. Dei, cap.</hi> 19. <hi>Epiſcopus nomen eſt operis, non honoris, vt intelligat non ſe eſſe Epiſcopum, qui praeeſſe dilexerit, et non prodeſſe.</hi> A Biſhops name, is a name of labour, not of honour. To teach vs, that hee is not a Biſhop, which ſtriueth to rule in the Church, and not to profit the Church by his labour and preaching. For as <hi>Proſper</hi> ſayth, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil Sacerdoti prodest, etiamſi bene vixerit, modo male viuentes tacendo non arguit.</hi> It doth not profit a Prieſt to liue well, vnleſſe, withall hee reproue euill liuers by his doctrine. Our Sauiours Commiſſion was, <hi>Math.</hi> 28. <hi>Goe teach and baptize all Nations, teaching them to obſerue all things I haue commanded you.</hi> Hence Saint <hi>Paul, Woe is me, if I preach not the Goſpell.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi> 20. When <hi>Paul</hi> ſent for the Elders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he firſt related his owne paines, <hi>That he was free from the blood of all men, and had kept nothing backe, which was neceſſary for their ſaluation.</hi> And then verſ. 28. he gaue them this great charge, <hi>Take heede vnto your ſelues, and to all the Flocke, whereof the Holy Ghost hath made you ouerſeers, to feed the Church of God, which hee hath purchaſed with his owne blood.</hi> And 2 <hi>Timothy</hi> 4. <hi>I charge thee before God, and before the Lord Ieſus, preach the Word in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, reprooue, exhort, rebuke, with all long ſufferance, and doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I but how often? <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, <hi>Pauci ſint ſermones tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Let thy Sermons be few: quarter Sermons, month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sermons? No, <hi>Be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon. We are labourers in Gods Vineyard.</hi> Take heed we heare not one day, <hi>Why ſtand you heere idle all the day long?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I, but all preaching? no praying? Indeede there are extremes: for ſome would haue all praying, no prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: others would haue all preaching, no praying: where the meane ſhould be obſerued: For God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid,
<pb facs="tcp:16582:8"/>
theſe two ſiſters ſhould bee like the two brothers, <hi>Aeteocles,</hi> and <hi>Polynices,</hi> which deadly hated one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Nay, I would not haue theſe two like <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> two louing brothers, yet, one muſt not liue, but the other muſt dye. But I wiſh from mine heart, that preaching and praying, might bee like <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> two twinnes, liue arme in arme together. For when <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> appeared ſingle to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, they prefigured ſhipwracke, or ſtormes: but if they both appeared, it noted proſperous weather. So, praying, and no preaching, would not ſo well edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Church: becauſe where viſions fayle, the people waxe naked: and preaching without praying, doth not well beſeeme Gods Church, whoſe houſe is <hi>the houſe of prayer:</hi> but both together: the one will teach vs how to pray, the other will fit vs how to heare. If one fagot will warme me, I hope, an hundred will more; ſo, if the Prayer of one iuſt man preuayle much with God, then the Prayers of an whole pariſh together will be more forcible. I, but all preachings? no reading of Pſalmes, Chapters, Epiſtles, Goſpels? Surely reading of Scriptures is a moſt bleſſed thing: yea to a large ſence it may bee termed preaching, as it is an open publication of GODS will: but for any man to ſay, that reading is ſo excellent, as that preaching Saint <hi>Paul</hi> commandeth: which is, to diuide Gods Word aright, by enterperting it, and applying it to the hearers ſoules: is, I hold, moſt inconuenient: for then what neede we be at charge, to get men of gifts, and to ſend them to the Vniuerſities? A child often, or twelue yeeres old may read diſtinctly, to the edification of the hearer. Therefore as ſpice whole, ſmelleth ſweetely: but bruiſed by an Apothecary, it is more pleaſant: ſo Gods Word read, is as ſweete as Hony: but preached, it is more comfortable. If the loafe of bread be whole and cruſty, the children can hardly bite it: but cut
<pb facs="tcp:16582:9"/>
it into ſlices, and euery infant can eate it: So it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt reading and preaching. See this in the two Diſciples going to <hi>Emaus, Luke</hi> 24.27. How did their hearts burne within them, when our Sauiour was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to them the Scriptures! See by the <hi>Eunuch</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but not vnderſtanding, yet at <hi>Philips</hi> preaching a true Chriſtian, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>This doctrine concerneth our ſelues, and the people: for our ſelues, Muſt wee bee labourers, and not loyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers? Muſt wee preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon? Then, woe worth that man which taketh this ſacred Function on him, without gifts furniſhed for the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacerdos ſi ſit praedicationis neſcius, quam clamoris vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oem daturus? eſt praeco mutus,</hi> ſayth <hi>Gregory:</hi> How can he giue or ſend Gods Word into the peoples eares and hearts, when he cannot preach? Will any be ſo idle, as to ſue to be Cryer of a Citty, when he hath no tongue in his head to ſpeake? Excuſe not thy ſelfe, becauſe the Biſhop hath conſecrated thee a Prieſt: For, as <hi>Gregory</hi> reporteth, An Emperour commanded an Ape ſhould be turned into a Lyon: <hi>Et quidem prouiſione illius vocari Leo poteſt, fieri autem non poteſt.</hi> The Emperour might cauſe the Ape to be called a Lyon, but he could not cauſe him to be made a true Lyon. So, the Biſhop may call, and cauſe thee to be called a Preacher: but ſurely, he cannot furniſh thee with learning, to make thee a Preacher. Theſe the holy Scriptures call dumbe dogs. But there are others of our Coate, whom God hath enabled with gifts ſufficient, and the Church with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and wealth in an high degree: yet theſe will beare no heate nor burden of the day, in Gods Orchard. Nay, they doe often hate ſuch as doe take paines, <hi>eo nomine,</hi> onely becauſe they doe take paines, and brand them with the odious name of Puritant. Theſe are not dumbe dogs: but as I may ſay, malicious dogs. Like
<pb facs="tcp:16582:9"/>
               <hi>Lucians</hi> dogge in the manger, which will neyther eate Hay himſelfe nor let the Oxe eate any. Nay, they are not dumbe and malicious dogges: but as one ſayth, dumbe diuels.</p>
            <p>There are many which ſpeake much againſt Puritants: and for my part, ſuch as are factious, I wiſh them at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam:</hi> but I am verily perſwaded, that none make more Puritants in the Church, and Common-wealth, then they that moſt ſpeake againſt them. For the people cannot diue into our controuerted opinions, but they can iudge our outward actions. Now then, when they ſee men of much meanes &amp; honour in the Church, to liue idly: and meane perſons in place and Liuing, to preach much: this maketh the people to iudge: Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe men doe beſt, and therefore they are in the right: whereas conſider, we which ſtand for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches diſcipline, are as well bred as the other: we haue Arts, and Sciences, and Bookes, natural parts and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of body. Now then, if wee would but labour in preaching, I am perſwaded, it would put downe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently all factious Schiſmatickes, and Separatiſts, which by our idleneſſe doe much abound: but let theſe which ſheare the Sheepe, and not feede the flocke, thinke what will become of them at the laſt day, when Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſhall appeare with three thouſand conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at one Sermon: when Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſhall appeare with whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions conuerted at their preaching, and theſe ſhall ſtand ſingle with the vnprofitable ſeruant, hiding his talent in a napkin, and cannot ſhew one ſoule, that he hath wonne, or endeauoured to winne to God. There is a ſtory how a learned Fryer in <hi>Italy,</hi> famous for his learning and preaching, was commanded to preach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pope at a yeere of Iubile: and to bee the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter furniſhed, he repayred thither a good while before to <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſee the faſhion of the Conclaue, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate
<pb facs="tcp:16582:10"/>
his Sermon the better, when the day came, he was to preach, hauing ended his prayer, he looking along time about, at laſt he cryed with a loud voyce three times, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was a foole, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was a foole, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was a foole. Which words ended, he came out of the Pullpet. Being after conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the Pope, and asked why he ſo carryed himſelfe? Hee anſwered, Surely holy Father, if a Prieſt may goe to Heauen abounding in wealth, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and preferment, and liue at eaſe, neuer, or ſeldome to preach, then ſurely Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was a foole, which tooke ſuch an hard way, in trauelling, in faſting, in preaching, to goe thither: and ſo ſurely if to haue many liuings and much honour in the Church, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of them, to take our fill of pleaſures, to heape vp wealth, and to liue at eaſe, ſeldome or neuer to preach Gods Word, be the way to Heauen, then ſurely we poore country Miniſters are very fooles, to toyle our bodies, and to beate our braynes with preaching and ſtudying to goe that hard way, when we may with more eaſe goe to Heauen in a feather-bed. But let theſe remember, that <hi>Praesbyteri, non ſanatis magis quam ſanandis hominibus praeſunt,</hi> ſayth <hi>Auſtine,</hi> Preachers are placed ouer men which are not perfectly ſound, but are to be made more ſound dayly, by their preaching and inſtructions.</p>
            <p>For the people.</p>
            <p>Are we Gods laborers? Then he which ſerueth at the Altar, muſt liue by the Altar. Hee that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Goſpell, muſt liue by the Goſpell. <hi>For the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer is worthy of his hyer.</hi> Heretofore no ſinne to great, as ſacriledge, no gift ſo good as to the Church: now no ſinne ſo ſmall, as to rob <hi>Peter,</hi> and not to pay <hi>Paul,</hi> but themſelues: and no gifts extracted ſo hardly, as the Miniſters due, the Shepherds were woont to liue by the flocke, but now the Miniſter can
<pb facs="tcp:16582:10"/>
hardly get wooll to cloath him, or Milke to feed him becauſe they challenge, cuſtomes and ſue out prohibi, tions, where the Iudge a Lay man, the Iury Laymen the witneſſes Laymen, the Lawiers Laymen: all Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men intereſt in the cauſe: our caſe is like to a poore ſheepe, which in the time of ſtorme, runneth vnder an hedge for ſhelter, when ſhee goeth away, ſhee leaueth ſome of her wooll behind her. I, but what ſay the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Stand to our beneuolence and courteſie, for we will deale well with you: I, and then men of the beſt gifts ſhall be ſure to bee preferred, and neuer to want.</p>
            <p>My beloued, woe worth our anceſtors, that founded Schooles and Vniuerſities: woe worth our parents which brought vs vp at ſuch charge, and at the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and woe worth our owne ſelues to take ſuch paynes, in ſtudying arts, and reading of authors, finding out tongues, and then to come into the Townes and Villages to be iudged, if we haue learning and gifts: And by whom? By good man the Cobler: By Maſter the Mercer, by clowted ſhooes and tuſſet coates. Thinke in your owne ſoules, is this fitting?</p>
            <p>For your dealing well and bountifully with vs: call to minde I pray, how the Woolues and the Sheepe made a League; for certaynety they gaue hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages; the Sheepe gaue their dogges, which defended them: the Woolues, their young ones, but after the Sheepes dogges were faſt tyed: the young Woolues crying, the old did preſently run and fetch away their young ones, and killed the Sheepe. Euen ſo part with our free-hold, and ſtand to your loue: then in ſtead of our fee ſimple, you will giue vs a ſimple fee. The Eagle ſtole fleſh from the Altar, but ſhe carryed away a coale, which ſet her neſt and young on fire. And wee all know, whoſe fathers were enriched by Church goods, their poſterity were beggers at the third generation. I haue obſerued it
<pb facs="tcp:16582:11"/>
in my experience, in this Country, and I could inſtance in many Gentlemen, and other perſons, which haue been moſt bitter againſt tithes, and ſtood to cuſtomes: that eyther they were men of no religion, or if they made ſhew of any, yet God hath ſent vpon them, or their poſterity, ſome fearefull iudgement, and therefore take heede, if we giue vnto you <hi>Panem Sanctuarij,</hi> the bread of Life, deny not vnto vs <hi>Panem promptuarij,</hi> the bread of Wheat for our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: <hi>For thou must not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the Corne.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth tell you, if you dare beleeue him, <hi>that if we ſow to you Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things, what is it if we reape Temporall?</hi> It is nothing in compariſon.</p>
            <p>The third thing that was obſerued, is the Preachers Wiſedome: <hi>Pleaſant words.</hi> There are ſome. I confeſſe, are very laborious in their Preaching, but yet <hi>Mulier formoſa ſuperne, Turpiter atrum deſinit in piſcem: Tincta Lycambao ſanguine tela dabunt.</hi> They muſt kicke and ſpurne at their Mother, and at her diſcipline, and ſo breed faction. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 5. <hi>All the Stones of the Temple were ſmooth, hewed and fitted, and then brought into the Temple and layd: For in the Temple was heard no noyſe nor Hammer.</hi> To teach vs, that in Gods Church there ſhould bee no <hi>Schiſme,</hi> nor rent, but all peace and quiet. Theſe men are lights in the Church, but like the flaſhing of a candles ſnuffe, which going out, leaueth a bad noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſauour behind it. Surely theſe doe not ſeeke out pleaſing words: Therefore into their ſecrets let not my ſoule come. But if any will labour to ſeeke out plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant words, the Words of truth, and will ſpeake to their Mother in vnity of doctrine, and in vniformity of diſcipline: Let Gods bleſſings be multiplied vpon him in as ample a manner, as the bright Starres are fixed in the glorious Firmament of Heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pleaſant words.</hi> Eſay 58. <hi>Cry, and ceaſe not, cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud.
<pb facs="tcp:16582:11"/>
Praeconis officium in ſe ſuſcipit, quicunque ad ſacerdotium aſcendit,</hi> ſayth <hi>Gregory:</hi> A Prieſt taketh on him the Office of a Cryer: therefore wee muſt be like <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, loud cryers in the wilderneſſe, to bid the people repent. We muſt be <hi>Boanarges,</hi> ſonnes of thunder, to awaken men out of their dead ſleepe of ſinne and ſecurity. What if men bee ſo nice as the Sybarites, which could not endure a Cocke in their City, for feare of too timely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waking in the morning? Yet, we muſt be like the Cock which crowed to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> he crew once, and he heard him not: twice, and hee was deafe: the third time, <hi>Then Peter went out and wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly.</hi> Yet this our crying, this our thundering, this our crowing, muſt bee like the buſling of a Gnat, which wakened the ſhepherd, when hee ſaw the Serpent comming. All muſt be done in wiſedome to warne them of the old Serpent: not in hatred, to exclaime againſt them, but in care to preuent their danger: not in ſtomacke, to breake our anger, but in loue, to awaken them: not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, to wrong them. <hi>The Preacher must ſeeke out pleaſant words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee are the Salt of the earth, therefore wee muſt be applyed to the vlcerous ſoares of their ſoules, to keepe them from feſtring in their ſinnes. And we muſt remember to be Salt, in another ſence, as it was <hi>Amoris monumentum,</hi> The embleme of loue: it is not to bee done in hatred to fret them, but in loue to ſeaſon them: <hi>The Preacher muſt ſeeke out pleaſant words.</hi> Wee muſt take into our hands the ſword of the Spirit, which is GODS Word, and this muſt cut and pierce them to the marrow and the bone. But theſe wounds muſt bee like the lancing of a Chyrurgion, <hi>In curam, non in cruo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,
<pb facs="tcp:16582:12"/>
dum producis verbera, extende vbera,</hi> ſayth <hi>Bernard:</hi> Wee muſt bee like the Mother, which hath a rodde to whippe the childe: and withall, a dugge, full of ſweete Milke, to nouriſh, and feede the childe. <hi>The Preacher muſt ſeeke out pleaſant words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This doctrine concernes both Prieſts and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>For vs, wee muſt <hi>ſeeke out pleaſant words.</hi> Then as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſayth, See the Miniſter obſerue <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quid</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ui</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quando</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Qualiter</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quamdiu</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>loquatur.</hi> 
               <list>
                  <item>What to ſpeake</item>
                  <item>To whom</item>
                  <item>When</item>
                  <item>How</item>
                  <item>How long.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Quid,</hi> What hee may ſpeake. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Let our ſpeech bee gracious and powdered with Salt:</hi> that as Salt doth extract hurtfull humors from the meat, and expell all corruption from it, ſo the grace of heauenly wiſedome ſhould repreſſe all idle and vnprofitable talke, and renounce all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and filthy communication, Genealogies, and fooliſh queſtions auoyde, which doe breede ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contention and ſtrife, then godly edifying which is by fayth. And as Salt doth dry vp the ſuperfluous humours of meats, and maketh meat fit to bee digeſted, and wholeſome to nouriſh: So, the Salt of Wiſedome ſhould make the Preachers words, not onely not hurtfull, but fit and profitable to edifie the hearers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui,</hi> Note to whom we ſpeake, not to all alike, 1. <hi>Timothy</hi> 5. <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but exhort him as a Father: the younger men
<pb facs="tcp:16582:12"/>
as brethren.</hi> Nay, that which is fitting to bee ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at one time, is vnfitting to bee ſpoken to the ſame perſon at another time. When <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſinned foulely, <hi>Nathan</hi> ſayd in an hye ſtraine, <hi>Thou art the man.</hi> But when he came to <hi>Dauid</hi> about <hi>Salomon,</hi> he bowed himſelfe in an humble manner, and ſpake mildly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Quando,</hi> When to ſpeake. A word in due ſeaſon, is like Apples of gold, with pictures of ſiluer: ſpeake nothing but truth. Yet all truth is not at all times to be vttred, but marke opportunity, learne wiſedome in this poynt, of a woman, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. <hi>Abigal,</hi> when <hi>Nabal</hi> was in his cups, let him alone: after hee had ſlept, ſhee ſpied occaſion to lay open his fault.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Qualiter.</hi> Note, after what manner to ſpeake. For as ſome Phyſicke cureth one, and killeth another. Nay, what Phyſicke doth cure the body at one time, doth hurt the ſame body at another time. So, the ſame doctrine which comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth one, woundeth another. Therefore, as the Chyrurgion, if hee ſee dead fleſh in the wound, applyeth not Balſome and healing ſalues: but red powders and corroſiues, to eate the fleſh to the bones: and after powreth in Balme, and layeth on ſaluing playſters. So, Preachers muſt not lull dead conſciences into dead ſleepe of ſecurity, with the comfortable promiſes of the Goſpell, vnleſſe they bee firſt humbled by the terror of GODS Law. Therefore, firſt preach the Law, then the Goſpell. Thus did God to <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe: ſaying, <hi>Adam, where art thou? Who told thee thou wert naked? Haſt thou eaten of the forbidden tree?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16582:13"/>
And then <hi>Adam</hi> conuicted in his conſcience, was comforted by the Goſpell, that <hi>The ſeede of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the head of the Serpent.</hi> Thus did <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid, Thou art the man; thou haſt killed Vriah the Hittite, and taken Berſhaba his wife.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> being humbled by the ſight of his ſinne: crying, <hi>I haue ſinned,</hi> was then lifted vp by the Goſpell, <hi>Thou ſhalt not dye, for the Lord hath taken away thy ſinne.</hi> Thus did <hi>Peter</hi> the 2. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> hee told the <hi>Iewes</hi> they had killed <hi>the Lord of life:</hi> and then pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their conſciences, they cryed, <hi>Men and brethren, what ſhall wee doe?</hi> Then <hi>Peter</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted them with the Goſpell, ſaying: <hi>Repent, and amend your liues, and bee baptized in the Name of the Lord Ieſus for the remiſsion of ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Quamdiu.</hi> Note heere. How long to ſpeake. We muſt not vnder zeale make Religion tedious, but as in the <hi>Hebrue, I haue written vnto you in few words,</hi> ſo, <hi>Quicquid percipias, breuis eſto:</hi> be ſhort, eſpecially if you come to viſit a weake and ſicke perſon.</p>
            <p>For the people.</p>
            <p>If wee muſt preach, and our preaching muſt bee pleaſing: yea it will bee ſo to the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, though not carnall man: then yee muſt heare with obedience. Yee muſt not bee like a galled Horſe, to kicke and fling when his ſtrayne is ſearched.</p>
            <p>If a Mayden tell her Miſtris, ſhee hath ſpots of durt in her face, and bring her a Glaſſe to ſee them, will ſhee breake the Glaſſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:16582:13"/>
chide the Maide? Will ſhee not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> water and a towell to wipe them away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> So, if wee tell you your ſoules ſinnes, and lay them open out of GODS Word, as a Glaſſe to conuince your conſciences, ſhall yee bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at vs, or ſhould you not ſtriue to waſh your ſoules cleare by teares of repentance, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life?</p>
            <p>If the Chyrurgion cut your fleſh, and tortor you, with ſetting your broken bones, yee are not angrry, but pleaſed with him. And ſo muſt yee not maligne the Preacher, if hee harrow your conſciences, bee it yrkeſome to fleſh and blood for a time. Wherefore as <hi>Lydia</hi> attended to what <hi>Paul</hi> preached: So, doe yee willingly hearken to your Paſtor. If his doctrine bite at the firſt, that yee ſay to him, as the Diuell did to CHRIST, <hi>Are thou come to torment vs before our time?</hi> Yet when GODS Spirit ſhall direct you, and turne your hearts, yee will ſay as <hi>Dauid</hi> did ſay to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, Bleſſed bee thou Abigal, and bleſſed bee thy counſell, and bleſſed be GOD which ſent thee to giue me this counſell.</hi> So, when wee preach, and you heare: wee teach, and you practiſe: wee reproue, and you amend: <hi>Vtraque conſeruant, et omnia ſaluata ſunt, cum Deus nec inueniat in plebe quod puniat, nec Sacerdos potest habere quod doleat,</hi> ſayth <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Both doe preſerue, and all things are ſafe, when GOD ſeeing the people to endeauour well, will in mercy finde no occaſion to puniſh and afflict them: and when the Miniſter, ſeeing the attention and practice of his flocke, ſhall haue no occaſion to grieue that his labours are in vaine in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16582:14"/>God grant in his mercies, that wee may ſo preach, and you may ſo heare, as God may bee glorified, his Church edifyed, and our ſoules comforted, through IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS CHRIST our Lord, and onely Sauiour, <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16582:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
